Okay, let's get started.
So, today is the second day on data.
Um, last time we talked about how data
doesn't really just fall from the sky.
You actually have to think about where
it comes from. Um, so in general, the
internet consists of live services. um
these
um the data on those services have to be
either dumped or crawled and then
there's additional step where you have
to process the data and we also talked
about various um social societal
considerations
um terms of service copyright you have
to either get a license or appeal to
fair use. So there's a lot of complexity
that goes into data. Um so today we're
going to look more at the data pipeline
from transforming the data, filtering
the data, dduplication and mixing. Um
and then we're going to top it off by
talking a bit about um post-training
data um in particular how folks are
using synthetic data these days. So the
first part is going to be mostly about
pre-training. That's what you should
have in mind.
So we talked a little bit about data
transformation already, but just as a
kind of reminder. So raw data doesn't
come as text. Even as if you've you've
scraped something. If you ever look at
inside Chromic Crawl, it's it's not
text. It's either HTML. Sometimes it
could be PDFs or directories in the case
of uh GitHub.
So most of the tension on transforming
data is dealing with HTML because most
of the web is in HTML
and for this processing there's a lot of
this is fairly heristic um there's
removing of boilerplate um like
navigation and ads um and extracting
content um which is like the main part
of the page and there's some you know
subtleties around what constitutes
content usually
um you get rid of the footers and
headers um and maybe menus and those
things and you try try to extract the
content but you could imagine in cases
where some of the the navigation
elements might be might be helpful to
learn what web pages look like. So what
is content and what is not content is
not always clear and then what do you do
about images and tables are on in web
pages. Um so inherently this is a lossy
process because you need to linearize
HTML which at least is either
hierarchical or visual if you think
about the rendered uh output and do a
sequence of tokens. In particular tables
are um a bit tricky to deal with. Simple
tables you can render um using markdown
but if you have nested tables then that
becomes quite uh challenging. you have
to give ups at some point or approximate
at some point. Um so typically HTML to
text processing is is rule-based and the
reason for this is that rulebased um
processors are very fast um and and also
um they you're not trying to do too much
here. You don't need too much
intelligence. So rule-based generally
works. Um now I think there could be a
case for model based um interventions at
this point. They have to be very fast
and they have to you know do something
um more more intelligent. But if you
ever look at data you'll notice there
are um imperfections in the data just
because any rule-based uh processing is
going to be um is have some failure
rate. As we showed last time, the
accuracy uh does matter depending on
which tool you choose. Um
if you use Brazil parse or Traflera,
then it's you know I guess Brazilia
parse on these extended DCLM you know
eval um works better um than the others.
Um I'll talk also briefly about PDFs. So
there this uh hugging face work um which
released a data set called find PDFs. Um
so PDF files if you have open them up
not in um PDF reader um looks looks kind
of like this. Um and this needs to get
kind of rendered. Um so PDFs can be
found on just like web pages on the the
internets and common crawl u does um
have you know some PDFs. Um, generally
common call focus on text, but sometimes
if you're just given a URL, you might
not even know before you fetch it
whether it's a PDF or or not if it
doesn't have the extension.
Um, there's a lot if you read this blog
post there's a lot of details which I'll
spare you of. Um, for example, one thing
is that uh many of the PDFs that are in
comic crawl are truncated because PDFs
are big. So then that re demands that
rec crawling is necessary and then
there's a question once you have the PDF
file how do you actually convert it to
text um and you know some PDFs are might
be just scans as well right so they're
essentially images so there's a bunch of
tools that um this paper uh tried out um
but mostly this kind of involves um
running OCR um using a VLM and this
obviously can be much more expensive
than what we were doing before with
text. Fortunately PE or unfortunately uh
the PDFs are a very small fraction of
the whole internet but um they are very
valuable um because generally if you
bother to make a PDF that means you
probably have something um interesting
to say as opposed to a web page. So the
uh quality of a PDF is average PDF is
generally higher than uh for um for a
HTML file.
there's a lot of clean up and filtering
and PDFs more so even then than web
pages a lot of layout information is
missing um because uh in HTML you have
various tags like H1 and P that gives
you some semantic information PDFs are
by design all about layout so you don't
necessarily um they preserve the the
kind of the semantic structure
okay so there's a bunch of
transformation information that happens
at this point. You have uh text um um
and but you're not done. You're far from
done. So the next step is filtering.
So um I'm going to talk somewhat
abstractly about what filtering is.
Here's a sort of the building block. So
suppose you have some target data that
you uh want to get. Um this is usually a
small amount of high quality data and
lots of raw data. This is the the the
fresh shipment of the uh the tokens that
you do transform from the the previous
step and the goal is to find uh a subset
of this raw data that is similar to
target. So this is the general skeleton
for filtering and may almost all kind of
filtering falls into this uh this uh
schema.
So filtering, you could there's many
reasons you might want to filter. Uh if
you're training um an English language
model or a German language model, you
might want to identify the language and
filter things that don't match that that
language. Um the main reason for
filtering is is quality filtering. You
want to find things that are high
quality as opposed to low quality. You
don't want just uh you know spam. You
want um encyclopedia information. Um and
and then another application is uh
toxicity filtering. Of course, the
internet has plenty of nasty content and
maybe you don't want to train your
language model on that.
Okay, so for a filtering algorithm, you
want that you want some generalization
from the target data, right? Because you
already have the target data. You don't
want to just only get the target data
but um you also want it to be extremely
fast because you have to run it on the
whole internet. So this could be uh 100
trillion tokens worth of worth of data.
So generally filtering is you end up
with a very small fraction single digits
fraction of your entire um data.
Okay. So, so remember the general
framework given the target uh and raw
you're trying to find a subset. Okay. So
the general scheme is that you estimate
some sort of model based on R&T and
derive a scoring function and then you
keep the examples in R based on their
score. So typically there are two uh
types of classifiers. One are generative
models. Uh so this is basically um you
have your target data you can just um
you know estimate a model of that data
and remember this has to be cheap so
probably you're not training a big
language model generally um klm
basically says I'm going to train a five
gram uh model
um a more common thing um which I think
we're mostly seeing these days is just
train a classifier and The classifier
says, I'm going to predict a positive
label for examples that are in t my
target and negative labels for things
that are in raw but not in t. So you
basically it looks like t are your
positive examples. Um some random subset
of r your negative examples. You maybe
balance it and then you train a
classifier.
And the tool that people generally use
is fast text because it's fast uh and
it's generally it's just a linear
classifier bag of words. And then once
you have this model now for every new
document you can score it and you set
some appropriate threshold depending on
your quality bar and you keep the
examples sometimes stochcastically
sometimes not.
Okay. So, so this is a very much a model
based filtering approach. Remember from
the last lecture, there are many data
sets um from you know generally a few
years ago that did not use modelbased
filtering because they wanted to not
bias things too much. These days I think
uh basically everyone does some amount
of modelbased filtering because um uh
unless you are compute plentiful which
in which case you probably don't need to
do as much filtering. You can just train
on everything. Most people are compute
uh poor um you have to be very smart
about how you're filtering. Otherwise
you're just wasting flops on kind of
lowquality content.
Okay, so let me talk through some
instantiations of of filtering. So
remember I mentioned language
identification. Um so the goal is just
to find given a piece of text, detect
whether it's of a particular language.
Um so Meta has trained these set of fast
text language identification models
which often you can just use off the
shelf. So it supports 176 different
languages. It's been trained on uh a
bunch of multilingual sites. So,
Wikipedia, remember, has a lot of
languages. There's also translation
sites um and sites for different
languages. So, um a language ID is is
generally a fairly easy problem compared
to many other tasks that we're dealing
with. So, a simple classifier, if you
look at a few words, you can tell that
it's Spanish or or or Japanese. Now this
does you know there are subtleties
because of code switching and text and
there's some dialects. So it's I
wouldn't say it's like an absolutely
solved problem but you know this is not
really the bottleneck for training a
good language model.
Um okay and then you can just so once
you have your classifier you just choose
some threshold. Um this is generally
fairly heristic.
So um another thing you can do with
filtering is that suppose you're looking
for data of a certain type. So let's say
you want to get really good at math. So
you go want to go and find a bunch of
math data. So uh open math text is this
um paper from 2023 where the goal is to
create a large corpus of math text. Um
this pipeline is consists of a few
steps. Um so it's not training a single
classifier. So first you use some rules
to filter does it contain latte
commands. Um you they also use kenlm. So
this is a generative approach um and
trained it on the proof pile which is a
known data set of math and keep it if
the perplexity is uh you know below some
threshold. Um and then you also train a
fastax classifier to predict whether
it's mathematical writing um or not. And
there's, you know, two different
thresholds. If it has latte in it, then
it's a higher bar. If it's uh sorry, if
it's it's a lower bar, but if it's uh
doesn't have latte in it, it's a higher
bar. Um and then as a result, they got
you know 15 billion uh tokens which they
use to train models. And as a paper they
show that um this more targeted security
data collection results in models that
are better than math at math than models
that were trained on 20 times much data
which were not filtered in this way.
Okay. So the the quality filtering again
think about it as a tool. Um you can
define quality however you want. There's
no universal notion of quality. If you
want define quality to be math then you
can go and get math and you get better
at it.
Um so GPT3 I think I mentioned this last
time but just to put it in this
framework. So positive examples are
Wikipedia
um web text. So these are pages that um
link out from high uh you know star
Reddit posts and some books and
negatives are generally sampled from the
the web. Um they train a linear
classifier and keep documents if the
linear classifier is scored um highly
enough. Um there's the first llama paper
the positives were pages referenced by
Wikipedia not Wikipedia articles
themselves um and the it's just kind of
the same idea. So uh 51 from Microsoft
um is interestingly had um you know also
falls into this framework. So um they
um started with the raw data is not
already a Python subset of the stack
remember which is this uh all you know
code and um they they're uh
the the prompt they define a prompt
which is determine educational value and
then they use GPD4
to classify uh a subset of R 100k subset
of the R with this prompt.
and see if it's uh and the ones that are
positive are kept and called the target.
Right? So the target here is actually
output of an expensive um you know
classifier
and then you train a cheaper classifier
in their case a random forest but you
could have probably used fast text as as
well. Um and uh and then you select data
that is um classified positive by this
this classifier. And they also show that
using this uh data set you do uh much
better than if you're just using um the
raw data. So this performance goes up in
fewer steps to a higher value.
Okay. So toxicity kind of works the same
way. There's this data set Jigsaw toxic
uh comments um where it came from this
project where the goal is to help people
have better discussions online. So here
the data is the Wikipedia talk pages um
which can I guess for controversial
sites get quite uh heated and this has
been annotated with whether there are
any any toxic comments on there and you
can similarly define positive and
negative examples and you can train a
classifier on that.
Okay. So, so now I think you have the
tools or some examples and inspiration.
You can identify um a particular type of
data that you want. You build a
classifier for it and then you can go
filter common crawl for that.
I want to talk about one uh subtlety
here u which is that you know the notion
of what you want for data is actually
depends on what model you want to train.
So in particular, it depends on the
number of tokens uh you're training on.
And so there's no optimal threshold. So
before when I looked at the the
classifier gives you a score um there's
you can't say 0.9 and say that's the
best because it depends on what you want
to do. Intuitively
if you are going to train for a longer
period of time then you can tolerate
lower quality data. If you're training
for shorter then uh you you want higher
quality data in general. Okay. And of
course you know if if you could wave of
magic one if you're training for longer
you want more high quality data but
that's not an option that you're given
the data pool is what it is.
So here's an a kind of a a preliminary
experiment um uh that Michael Ryan did
and uh so basically this plot shows for
a 157 million parameter model um we're
taking a very small uh pool so uh 100 uh
you know works which is a tiny fraction
of common crawl and um we're look
training and training um for more
uh over time. So let's take a look at
the blue curve. So the blue curve is
DCLM. And so the the loss starts here
and then it comes down and each of these
lines is when you uh epoch over the
data. So this is one epoch and then the
next blue is the second epoch and so on
and so forth. So there's not that much
data. So eventually you have to repeat
your data and um you know the loss
continues going down um because the
second time you look at the data you're
still learning things and at some point
you start to to overfit.
Okay. Um whereas if you look at
resilient pars this is basically no
filtering. Um so here it's it's much
worse in the beginning. Um but as you
continue and continue um at some point
you also epoch um it starts to go down
you know slower. So you kind of see this
trend where high quality data is better
in this regime where you're not epoing
but once you get to lots and lots of
tokens um high quality data is no longer
that uh great. And of course you with
high quality data you you wouldn't even
get you wouldn't want to go into this
regime because you're overfitting.
You'll probably stop here. But even this
at this point this is worse than if you
had trained for longer using low quality
data.
>> Yeah.
>> Just a question about like the um
computing the metrics. This is actually
not like totally about graph but like
when you're like each of those dots
correspond with one training one
training run, right?
>> Yes. um do you ever need to do the
confidence interval when you're doing
these kind of pre-training experiments
or like is it kind of enough just to do
it one time?
>> So the question is each of these points
is a single training run and uh should
you do it multiple times and get
confidence intervals? Um ideally that
would be good practice. Um often you'll
see in these papers that um these are
kind of scarce because each training run
is fairly expensive. Um so you but but
in reality when we have done these
experiments it's generally tends to be
stable I would say at least for
pre-training.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So you mentioned uh like trading
for longer and high quality data as
that's not like a combination that we're
considering but like like if if we are
trading with uh for longer on this high
quality data um would it have
diminishing returns compared to like
training for longer with quality data?
>> Yeah. So the question is if you were
able to get higher quality data and you
train for longer would it still have
diminishing returns? Um, every data set
is going to have the machine returns
eventually. Uh, that's finite. Um, but
it would just it would probably be here.
It would just like be down here and just
just keep on going down.
Okay, great. Let's let's move on. So,
summary, filtering is is pretty critical
for building a good model, especially
when you're computed like most of us. Um
technically if you have infinite compute
you don't need to filter and you can
train on everything and it'll be a giant
model but um realistically everyone has
to filter.
Um so and the recipe here is figure out
what good data looks like and then you
can train a classifier and that will
extrapolate to the rest of your model.
and what the good data looks like. You
can either find it by saying, "Aha,
there's this data set out there that I
really like and I just want more of it."
Or you can craft a prompt um to a
language model and then use that to
construct um to do a sort of a
preliminary filter of a large pool and
then use that uh good quality data to
train a smaller classifier and
extrapolate to everyone else.
Okay, next I'm going to talk about
dduplication. So at this point we have
uh filtered our data set so we only have
what we deem to be high quality data. Um
but you know
often data still has duplicates in it
and um there's you know two types of
duplicates. There's exact duplicates. So
this happens when um for example if you
look at these um mirror sites the whole
point of a mirror is that it's a
duplicate and you know sometimes the web
crawler isn't smart enough to know that
this mirror is exactly this mirror so it
just crawls um many uh sites and you'll
get this exact same content.
Um also when you fork a repo um that is
also um a a duplicate. um even if you
make changes probably you're making
changes to a few files so 99% of that
repo might be uh the same. So duplicate
is is um abundant um and yeah sometimes
there's actually near duplicates which
are not mirrors or derivative but they
just happen to be uh same text differing
by a few tokens. Um, usually probably
this came from a kind of a uh it could
be copying or came from a different uh
common source. So here's some examples
of near uh you know duplicates. So terms
of service and licenses. Um so I guess
the MIT license probably shows up um you
know on a lot of places. Um and so many
cases it is a exact um copy but only of
that license unless someone made a typo
when they copied it. Um but the rest of
the page um that the license might be
part of is might be different. And we
talked about how a lot of websites have
the same um headers and footers. Those
are also you know duplicates. Um there's
also cases where for whatever reason um
you know there's uh this is from LM1B so
the one billion or benchmark there's
like these articles where you just have
you know typographic uh differences like
uh there's one version with a comma and
one version without a comma I don't
really know why but uh that's happens
and sometimes you see these templates
where there this is like some you know
probably low quality content where it's
like a it's a essentially looks like an
ad of some sort and someone just uh you
know templatize replace Canada with USA.
Um so if you train like on this data but
you are just training on different
variations of this with different
entities this is going to be wasting
your GPUs.
There's a more extreme cases. So this is
why it's good to look at your data. So
this audit of the C4 data set found this
product description 61,000 times in the
data set. And if you trace back, this is
really bizarre. I don't know why this is
like some um description of this gas
mask. And this just showed up in this
data set um in common crawl 61,000
times. So um yeah, the web is weird. Um
so why do duplicate? So the first clear
uh idea is clear because you want to
train more efficiently. Duplication
reduces your data set size without
really losing information because you're
just removing duplicates. And it also
has this benefit of avoiding um
memorization which this uh paper you
know talks about. Um for example, if you
have some um copyright content that's
duplicated a lot then if you train on it
then you memorize it and also privacy
concerns. uh but mostly I think uh it's
uh just to uh
make sure that you're not uh wasting
flops related to due duplication that's
also decontamination which is arguably
even more important to and it's the same
sort of uh deal is that you want to make
sure that your uh test set is not in
your training set.
Okay. So so how do we ddup? So here's
the design space to think about. So
first of all, what are the items that
you're dubbing? Do you do at the
sentence level, the paragraph level, or
the document level? Um, how do you
determine a match? Is it an exact match?
Is it existence of a common sub item? Is
it the fraction of common sub items u
for near dduplication? And then once you
found a duplicate between two pages,
what do you do? Do you remove all the
instances or do you remove all but one?
Okay, so um and the key algorithmic
challenge is that dduplication is
fundamentally about comparing items to
other items.
Um and
normally if you're doing filtering this
is about an individual item. This item
is it good or not? And this can be
paralyzed. It can be you know it's sort
of linear time which is good. Um and
even in linear time we're trying to make
it fast by having rule-based or very
small models. But due duplication
clearly you can't do the n square thing
where you compare everything to
everything. You need linear times uh
algorithms to scale especially at this
web scale.
So um typically the dduplication
literature um uses hash functions to get
around this. Um so we'll develop some of
these uh ideas. These are quite nice
ideas um from um thanks to um you know
the algorithms uh community. So I think
everyone knows what a hash function is.
It takes of some sort of value like a
string and maps it into something like a
string or integer. Um and a hash value
is much smaller than item. Hash
collisions are when two distinct items
map to the same age. Okay. So uh when
you look at hash functions there are
really fancy hash functions which are
cryptographic uh nature. These are
collision resistance used in cryp um uh
cryptography and um and bitcoin and
things like that. And then there's these
like uh faster ones which are used for
hash tables where hash collisions aren't
the end of the world. And so we'll be
using um these. Okay. So take a string
and map it to some value. That's what um
hash functions do.
Okay. So exact duplication is is
conceptually very simple. Um you you
take a string um you see if there's an
exact match and you remove all but one.
Okay. So here you have a bunch of um
elements and you you hash them and you
ddup. Okay. So this is um and exact
duplication is is is very nice. It's
very clear what's happening, but this
isn't really good enough for the messy
web data because often you have these
near duplicates. Um and one note is that
there's many ways to have um you know
written this. Um this is written by in a
sort of like um a bit of a map reduce uh
style way which makes it more easy to
easily paralyzable and scale. Um so C4
um
this uh this paper from the the T5 paper
um which process common crawl did exact
duplication. the items they operate on
were three sentence spans. Um, and you
uh do um exact match and they remove all
but one.
So, one, if you're kind of paying
attention, you realize that there's
something kind of a bit strange about
this because you're looking at three
sentence spans. And if you find two
documents with three sentence span, you
remove all but one. That means you're
just going to rip out three sentences
from that document, which is a little
bit strange because it breaks the
coherence, but you know, this is what
they did.
Um okay so that's exact dup dd
duplication. So how do we do near uh
dduplication? So first of all we have to
define what approximate uh match means
here. Okay. So to do that um we're going
to define this uh called jakard
similarity which is a fairly standard
notion. And jakard of two sets is
basically the size of the intersection
over the size of a union. Okay. So given
these two sets uh 1 2 3 4 and 1 2 3 5.
Uh when you compute jakard you take the
intersection that's 1 2 3 you take the
union that's 1 2 3 4 5 and you divide
and the jakard is 0.6.
Okay. So the chakard is a number between
0 and one. Zero means that they're
disjoint. one means that they're
identical. Okay, so a fairly natural
notion and um we're going to say that
two documents are near duplicates if
their jakard similarity is above some
threshold let's say 0.99.
So now the question is how do you find
near duplicates in linear time? Okay, so
fortunately this is a solved uh you know
algorithms question and the answer is to
use um minash.
So um
well okay so the first step is to use
minash that's not the final answer. So
minash is a random hash function
so that the probability of a hash
collision is exactly uh the jakard of am
and b. So this is a very kind of nice
property because um hash functions
hashing is good for making things linear
time. Jakard is the metric that we want
and we're sort of connecting these two
uh right now or in expectation. So
what's interesting is that normally you
want hash functions to define hash
functions so that everything is um
hashing to different distinct elements
are hashing to different things. You
don't want collisions but here you
actually want collisions u not arbitrary
collisions but you want to control the
collisions in a certain way to align
with a similarity. So similar things you
want to collide more than the disperate
things.
Okay. So um so the minash is essentially
you um actually let's see maybe I will
okay so here's the the min hash. It's
fairly simple. You take the set and you
hash every element in that set and you
take the minimum element. Okay. So um
this mean might if you're seeing this
for the first time it may seem a little
bit strange. Why are you taking the min
um you can take a max too doesn't really
matter it's just a way to break um ties.
So here's the the picture that uh you
should have in your mind. So okay so if
you have um
um a remember a contains one two three
four and b contains 1 2 3 5. So this is
a characteristic matrix representation
of these two sets, right? And so what
the random hash uh function is is doing
is that it induces a permutation over
the items.
Okay, so it might be 4 3152
or something else. And then you look at
which item is first according to this
permutation in A and which item is first
in B.
So each item has the same probability of
being first. Okay. So if you have if it
the random hash function puts one first
then um first in
A will be equal to first in B. And if
it's two first then it's the same. If
it's three first it's also the same. But
if it the random permutation puts four
first then the first element in A is
going to be different from the first
element in B. And same with five.
Okay. So look at this representation.
Basically the random hash function says
elect one of these rows to be you know
first and then when I the min is just
telling me the min um the the the min
equal of a equal the min of b is
basically telling me whether that row
has um is the same.
Okay, so that is the I guess the proof
of um why minash why this property holds
which is that you have a hash function
in expectation over your random choice
of hash functions that um the
probability of collision is the
similarity metric you want
okay so let's just check this in code so
um I'm going to generate 100 different
hash uh you know functions S each hash
function is given by a seed um and I
just check whether the minash is equal
to minash and the estimated jakard. So
um I'm going to just look at the number
of the fraction of matches and you get
0.6.
Okay. And the key thing with a minash is
that um I don't have to do the the n
squared thing. I can compute the minash
of A and the minash of B and minash of a
different set and I just look for
collisions.
Okay, any questions so far about
Minhash.
So now we can hash our items, but we're
not done yet because a collision doesn't
tell us that jakard is above some
threshold, which is what we want. We
want to find a and b such that jakard is
greater than 0.99. All we've done is
said, okay, well, if we got a collision,
the probability of that collision of two
things colliding is the jacard. But
that's not really that useful by itself.
it's sarcastic and I can't really get
anything reliable here.
So um the next thing idea is this thing
called locality sensitive hashing which
essentially solves this uh problem. So
this is a very classic idea in
theoretical computer science and it's
quite nice. Um so the idea here is that
we have a and b colliding with
probability equal to jakard. Okay, so it
is true that more similar items will
collide more often,
but it's very stochastic, right? The
variance is, you know, quite large here.
So our goal is to have A and B collide
if the Jakard is greater than some
threshold. So we in some in some sense
have to sharpen these these
probabilities somehow like the
probability can't just be literally
equal to the jakard.
So the solution is to use more hash
functions
u and these hash functions are going to
be independent.
So um this part is you know gets a bit
technical but um we'll walk through it.
So you break the n hash functions into u
b bands of r hash functions. So if you
have 12 hash functions you have three
bands. Each band has our uh four hash
functions. Okay. So there's a band here
H1 through H4. Here's a second band H5
through H8. Third band H9 through H12.
Okay. And then so what we're going to
try to do so so each hash function gives
us either um collision or not collision.
Okay. Um and so every hash function
there's a probability of uh colliding.
So the key here is that we want to say
um compute the probability that A and B
collide. We say that A and B collide if
for some band all of its hash functions
return the same value.
Okay. So um if H5 and H6 and H7 and H8
all return um the kind of the same
value. So sorry if h a of a equals h5 of
uh sorry h5 of a equals h5 of b and h6
of a equals h uh six of b and so on that
means this band is triggered and then I
would say they collide or if this band
if all of these say um coll uh agree
then I say it's collision or these two
but you don't have to have all the hash
functions uh um you know uh return the
same value.
Okay, so there's sort of this and or
structure here that is um is is doing
the the lifting here and we'll see why
this uh this works.
So um so now let's say you have a
particular jakard of A and B
um what is the probability that A and B
collide according to this uh definition?
Okay. So we can calculate this. Um
so let's say that uh this jakard
similarity is 0.8.
Okay. And we have five uh you know bands
and each band has 10 hash functions.
So then we can say what is the
probability of a fixed band matching. So
that's 0.8 eight to the r because each
band has r hash functions. So the
probability that they all have to match
is uh 0.8 to r. Okay. So the probability
of a band of a fixed band matching is is
generally quite low. It's exponential in
r.
Okay. And then now the probability of
collision is the probability that some
band matches
and that's going to be the probability
of one minus the probability of so this
is a probability of um a band not
matching
and this if you raise it to the B
there's B bands this is a probability
that all of them don't match and then
one minus that is the probability that
some match
okay so the probability of collision is
you know four and you expect it to be
higher because you're given you know
beach tries to get a match.
Okay.
So if you plot this um this is what it
looks like. Okay. So you have um on the
x- axis the similarity here
um and we were looking at 0.8 eight um
and and you look at uh the probability
of a a collision here. So we would
expect that if it's similarly zero then
it should be zero. If it's one it's one.
But notice that this is kind of a
interesting sshaped
which is is nice because this is what we
wanted to sharpen. We wanted to
basically say if the similarity is below
some threshold then we want the
probability to match to be as low as
possible. And if the similar is above
some threshold, we want it to be as high
as possible. So we're trying to get this
to be like a phase transition.
Okay. And if you you know plot this this
function as a function of similarity,
that's um what you get.
Okay. So um
Oops. Okay. So,
so let's just look at some examples. So,
let's uh concretely
we have um similarly 0.7 to 0.98. Okay.
Um and we're going to look at how u b=
10 r equ= 10.
So we um look at the collision
probability according to our definition
and we see that um this gives us a range
of um you know 0.25 to to one.
Okay. So if you were to set a threshold
you know this is this is not you know
bad. uh we can like set it here and you
know these with um you know some
probability will uh you know there's
still false positives because even if
these are below a threshold let's say
0.9 these might still collide but we can
filter them out um if we if we want but
um the ones above are mostly kept.
So what happens when you move uh
so increasing r so remember r is a
number of hash functions within a
bucket. So when you increase r um the
the threshold sharpens and moves the
curve to the right everything becomes
harder to match right because you have
more hash functions inside a bucket you
have that it sharpens that exponent. So
the probabilities you see here are kind
of sharper here. And now everything
moves to the to the right. Um, and now
it's fairly unlikely that if something
has loaded your card, you're going to to
match it.
So before it was like 0.25 and now it's,
you know, 08. Okay. So we're sharpening
the probabilities
and then increasing B has the effect of
moving the curve to the left. It makes
it easier to match. B is the number of
bands and some band has to match. If you
have more bands then there's more
chances of matching.
So if you look at this then um before
and after. So now we're making before
this 0.9 was only 72 and now it's 0.92.
And of course this this also increases
but you know not by that much.
Okay. So and you can drive these uh
phase transition to be as you know as
sharp as you want by increasing B and R.
But of course, if you can increase BNR
too much, then it can be more expensive.
But okay, so let's look at a more real
world setting. So in this paper on
dduplication,
the they had um you know B 20 bands and
R is 450. So to give you an idea of the
magnitude of these um these numbers
um and
In general this phase transition happens
at the at a threshold which is one over
b raised to the power of one over r. So
if you want to uh find a you know if you
want to filter based on jakard greater
than 0.9 then you basically have to set
bnr such that this is 0.9 and then by
changing BNR you can make that phase
transition uh sharper.
Okay. So remember probability that a
fixed band matches is one over b. If you
have at this threshold then the
probability that a and b collide is um
you know uh approximately
uh it's a it's a constant. So the
probability of collision is 64.
Okay. And this this makes sense that
basically if you have a phase transition
um the sort of center of that phase
transition is like point you know 64 and
everything below it should go to zero as
BNR increases and um everything above it
should go to one as BNR increases.
Okay any uh any questions about LSH?
So this this method is called minash LSH
um because LSH really works for any hash
functions. For um the duplication of
language model processing, we're using
the minash which approximates your card.
And so um that uh that basically is the
one you should use here.
Okay. questions about um DDUP.
So one note about DDUP is that
um there's often as we'll see data sets
that are coming in and sometimes the um
duplication will happen within a data
set but you actually have to do
duplication across your entire data set
because often data sets can be
redundant. So um you know sometimes
that's not uh done but it should be.
Okay, let's go on to the next topic
which is data mixing. Okay, so so far
we've transformed our data from really
uh you know raw HTML or PDFs into text.
We filter for high quality. we dduped.
So we have a smaller set of high quality
um documents and um
and this generally happens um for a
given you know data source but language
models are trained on multiple data
sources. So um in Marin um currently uh
this this website tracks the different
uh data sources that um the next model
will be trained on and you can see that
um there's a bunch of things there's
some neatron there's fine PDFs which we
talked about um there's some uh you know
institutional books um
and um some code and all these things.
Okay, so you have all these different
you know sources
um and the question is
how do you combine these?
So if you look at an older paper the
pile
um this is the
set of sources that they had at that
time
um and
they essentially assign a particular
weight to each component. So basically
you have a distribution of resources.
Okay. And so where does that weight come
from?
So more you know just cut and dry let's
say you have three sources you want to
find a data mixture and a data mixture
is just a distribution over your
sources.
Okay. So if you're just thinking about
this problem uh from first principles
um well not from first principles but
like just from what would you what you
might do um vibes which is I guess
opposite of first principles is you just
manually set it based on some intuition
which is more often than you might think
what people do right so I think this is
this is definitely fairly vibes based um
And even more recent papers um you know
you just look at it maybe you use some
method and then you just like tweak
things. Um you can also um do uniform
sampling which is you just put a uniform
distribution over your sources um and
you sample every um you know chunk you
you get you just sample a source. Um you
can also do uh proportional mixing which
is that you sample proportional to the
number of tokens in a source. So if you
have a data set with more you know
tokens then you put higher weight. So
this is also you know generally a
rational thing to do but you might worry
that the if you have a a huge lowquality
data set that's going to eat up a lot of
your tokens. So this doesn't seem quite
optimal either.
So intuitively
you should upweight your higher quality
sources.
Okay. But there's two things that um are
important to keep in mind. One is that
you do want to ensure some diversity,
right? So often sources are incomparable
for literature, code, and papers. um you
can't really say that uh you know this
paper is higher quality than this code
because they're just incomparable you
know objects maybe and if you want your
language model to do well you don't want
to just put all your um uh your mass on
just papers
the second thing which we'll talk a bit
more about is uh each source is actually
finite so if you put too much weight on
a small source then you need to you
essentially run out of that source and
you're you need to just epoch over it.
Meaning that you keep on training on the
same literally the same tokens and this
is going to be bad for reasons we'll uh
see. Okay, so let's let's uh try to
unpack this a little bit more concretely
this last point. So imagine you had just
have two sources a lowquality source you
have 10 trillion tokens and you have a
high quality source that has 10 billion
tokens. Generally high quality sources
are smaller.
Okay. So if you just do a naive data
mixture, let's just do uniform. So half
on high, half on low.
And I'm going to train for one trillion
tokens. Um so when I say train for one
trillion tokens, that doesn't mean
unique tokens. I just means uh train for
that many steps divided by batch size
essentially or times batch size. Um
okay. So then you look at let's look at
this which is the number of
times a particular element in the
lowquality data set was trained on. So
that's the number of epochs uh a
particular data uh point was trained on.
So p low times train tokens is the
number of uh times I'm want to request
uh tokens from um this lowquality source
and divided by the total number of
lowquality sources. So um this is less
than one. So basically that means um 5%
of the tokens in this lowquality data
set I'm even going to touch and train on
once.
Um, and then if you look at high
quality, you'll see that uh the number
of epochs is 50, right? Because I only
have 10 billion tokens here. And if I'm
half half, that means 500 billion
tokens. Um, I'm I need to train up 500
billion tokens of high quality data. But
I don't have 500 billion tokens of data.
So I have to repeat each data point 50
times.
Okay, so this is actually really
important and you know some big model
trains range uh runs have kind of messed
this up is that you can't just like
naively look at the the data sets and
define a distribution and then you
sample because um if you just look at
the quality if you look at the data you
don't you don't you're sort of missing
how many data points are there. Okay,
does this make sense? Maybe pause for
questions. This is a kind of important
point.
Okay. So, yeah.
>> Um, I guess like does it like why do we
need
in the first place? like doesn't it
achieve comparable performance level way
I don't know fewer you know
>> so the question is why do you need 50
epochs and I guess the point is that you
don't need 50 epox um worst case it's
wasting compute sorry best case is
wasting compute and worst case you're
overfitting
um but 50 the reason it's 50 is that if
you just go in and you define this data
mixture then you're going to be end up
doing 50 epochs without realizing unless
you're paying close attention
So this is basically the lesson is like
look at how many epochs you're actually
doing on your data.
>> Yeah.
>> How does this how do the mixtures get
expressed during training? Like so when
you switch every step do you train like
steps of 10 saying oh I want to do 10
code 10 to see because I feel like it
was like is there also any intuition
between
>> what decisions are made there.
>> Yeah good question. So the question is
like how when you train how do the
mixtures get uh kind of realized and so
uh in general um you you sample um so
you have you want to fill a batch right?
So you can sample a essentially for each
element um which uh mixture component it
comes from and you fill up a batch with
um you know sequences from that mixture
component. Usually you every sequence
comes from one mixture component. You're
not sampling like per token.
>> I guess so each batch should be mixed.
So I guess the unexture assumptions are
at the batch level and then you just
train for that. It's not like oh there's
one step is
>> yeah in general you want to to reduce
variance you want to train from multiple
um you know a batch should have some
mixture in it. Yeah.
Okay. So so this idea I mean this
problem has been noticed uh you know
quite a long time ago. Um and so in this
paper they introduced a unimax and I in
there that that case it was uh they were
training in multilingual models. It was
like very clear that some languages uh
were very low resource. So um you had to
do something about this. So in this
paper they noticed that before um some
works would uh essentially um take the
proportional mixing and raise it to some
power um to kind of flatten it out the
distribution. Um but the idea in this
paper is that um let's be a bit more
kind of explicit about that. Let's
sample the sources uniformly but with a
hard cap on the number of epochs. Okay,
so this is the key idea here is that you
say I'm only going to take 20 epochs
over a particular, you know, data
source. So if you've done that, then you
know, too bad. You go you you don't get
any more um tokens. You move on to the
next thing. So this is sort of like a a
safety net in in some sense. So in
particular if you look at the number the
probability assigned to a source times
the number of training tokens that
should be less or equal to the cap.
Okay. And there's a simple procedure for
actually just determine the mixture uh
subject to this uh constraint.
Um okay so let's switch gears a little
bit and talk about how we define the
mixture in the first place. Right?
Because if you have 50 sources, there's
50 numbers you have to fill. And we
noticed that proportional mixing isn't
really enough. Maybe you can try to get
estimate some quality metric and then
you can sample proportional to that. Um
but that is also heristic.
So the the most principled uh methods
and most kind of easiest to understand
like what's happening is these
regression based mixing methods. So
ragmix um mix and other papers like this
and the idea here is is kind is
relatively simple. So first you let's
say you're trying to train a large scale
model. So you go to a small scale um
let's say one you know I guess let's say
300 million parameters um and you you
try different data mixtures. So let's
say you have three uh components. You
try different mixtures and then you
train these small models. So you train a
swarm of small models. Each model gives
you a loss on some target metric. It
could be some downstream evals, it could
be perplexity, whatever you want. Okay.
So you use these data points to
basically fit a regression where the
regression model maps these um inputs
which is the the data mixture weights to
the loss.
Okay.
So now you have basically a very cheap
model that tells you if I were to train
on this mixture what loss would I get?
then you can essentially optimize that
um you know um data mixture uh sorry
optimize that function for the optimal
data mixture
and then that is the data mixture you
use to train the large scale model.
Okay, so that's the kind of the simple
procedure and you'll notice some kind of
similarities with with scaling laws
where you're trying to do some cheap
computations to figure out some answers
and then uh you know scale up. Okay, so
there's a few design decisions here. One
is you know what are the mixtures that
you're trying out here? You need a
distribution over distributions here. Uh
so often people use some durlay uh
distribution.
Um you also have to define the
regression method. Um people have tried
linear models or boosted decision trees.
Um you have to figure out the target
here. Um often this is based on
downstream eval. So, we have to be very
careful not to overfit, right? Because
we're doing pre-training and then, you
know, supposedly pre-training is
supposed to be training this general
purpose model and we're not trying to
fit some downstream evals. And if you're
not careful, for example, if you have a
bunch of code evals, then well, guess
what? You're going to upweight all the
code data. That's, you know, not rocket
uh science. And if you then go and you
say I want to generate some poetry, you
might uh you know realize that you've
over over fit. So you have to be very
careful about this. So proportional
mixing and uniform mixing don't have
this problem because you're not looking
there's no downstream evals.
And the the final thing is that you know
how much of a difference between small
and large scale um is there and this is
a cost and accuracy trade-off. Of
course, if you train really really small
models, um this might not be
representative. But if you train large
models to do this, you well, there's no
point in doing any of this. You just
train you're basically doing
hyperparameter tuning at the largest
scale, which is too expensive.
Um so this Omix paper actually does a
nice um has this nice table which shows
you for a number of different um methods
that all fall into this kind of um
framework. um this the size of the proxy
models they're generally fairly you know
tens or uh uh tens of millions of
parameters. How many you know points do
you sample mixtures do you sample um m
here being the number of parameters in
your mixture sorry the number of domains
rather um and you can use dishlay you
can use exponential um and then the
regression model uh you can fit a log
linear model which um you know tends to
work uh pretty well um and then uh you
can use different ways is to solve this
optimization um you know problem.
Okay, so there's sort of two leaps of
faith here that you just have to be very
careful of is that um the regression
model was trained on a bunch of these
small proxy runs and you're optimizing
this. So the hope is that your the
minimizer um your optimal data mixture
that regression model is still accurate.
Um, and this is a little bit kind of,
you know, you have to be very careful
because, um, if you, let's say, sample a
random mixture, you'll probably be fine
because, um, because of, you know,
classic generalization, you sample a
mixture, you and you fit a function, it
should be able to predict in
distribution. But when you're
optimizing, you're essentially trying to
go to potentially the extremes where you
might not have as much coverage. So
that's one thing to be careful of. And
the other thing is that um optimal uh
data mixtures you just hope that they
transfer for small scale to large scale.
Um and this in general it seems like at
least at the scales that open community
works with um tends to be true or not
blatantly false. Um but clearly there
are uh scale dependent effects. If you
just think about the the the previous
slide when we were talking about
filtering, if you're training for many
more tokens, then probably low quality
data is is okay. So clearly the optimum
is not the same, but you just kind of
hope for the best here.
Okay, so hold on. There's one scale
dependent effect that we we already
talked about but and we need to address
here which is that um you imagine so we
have a lot of lowquality data 10
trillion tokens 10 billion tokens of
high quality data and if we train a
small model on low token counts you know
remember uh what what happens is that
you might this is a madeup um you know
uh example But um you might put a lot of
mass on your high quality data
because if a low token counts, you're
not epoching. So it's like, oh wow,
Wikipedia is so great. Let's just train
on Wikipedia. Um but if you then go and
train your large mixture on this large
model on this mixture, um then you're
going to end up epoing a lot on this
high quality data and you'll overfit and
that's definitely um bad.
So one way to fix this which is done in
the OMIX um this Omix uh paper um is you
can just uh cap the number of epox
solution. There's another solution here
which um goes by probably multiple names
but one name for it is simulate
epoching. And the the the principle here
is that make your small scale look like
your large scale. This is kind of a
general theme for the course. We saw it
in kind of uh when Tatsu talked about
MUP. Um you parameterize your model so
that your your hyperparameters transfer.
And so the kind of same principle
applies here. And the problem with uh
you know doing this kind of naive
scaling is that um at low you can't be
not epoing at small scale and epoch then
epoing at large scales because then
those are qualitatively different um
operations on your data set. So the way
you would handle this is you um you
downstream your sources proportionally.
So
um so if you have your small runs were
10 billion tokens um and your big run
were one trillion tokens then you have
um a you know one in 100 kind of
downsampling um and
and then uh you basically use the down
sample mixture. And so the idea is that
if you have the down sampled you know
data um then this solution is not going
to look good because you're not training
on all you're not you don't get to just
train on all Wikipedia you're going to
train on some minuscule fraction of
Wikipedia and you'll realize oh actually
I'm going to be epoing a lot and that's
going to have really bad uh loss which
means that in the optimization you're
going to look for more balanced uh uh
approaches. is so you're kind of
simulating the data scarcity that you
would get at in your high regime at a
low scale.
Okay.
So to summarize this section um the
problem is how do you weigh different
sources? You have Wikipedia, you have
your common crawl, um you have your your
code, you have some math data that you
you scrape from somewhere. Um how do you
balance them? Um regression based mixing
is is a nice framework I think to think
about things. You you estimate your a
function form uh that maps your mixture
weights to a loss at small scale
optimize and then you generalize to
large scale. And you just have to be
very careful with uh this uh because of
epoing and overfitting kind of issues.
And you have to either use capped epoing
or simulate epoing.
So one lesson here is that um if you're
trying to optimize anything you have to
be very careful because you are in
danger of optimizing the the wrong uh
thing.
Okay. Any questions about data mixing
before I move on?
um when you're a dev sample assume
something is like too small that like
you can't really generalize as well.
>> So uh the question is if you're
downsampling is there's a risk maybe you
get too small of a data set. Um yeah
absolutely.
So
um I think right you might get into a
case where you just have so few tokens.
Um I think then what will happen is that
your optimum will just put very small
mass on that and when you scale up maybe
you get the right set of tokens. So in
principle like it should work out but
there might be like rounding errors
where like you end up instead of
training once on this data set you train
like zero times by accident. But you can
you can sort of work around these by
just like um think you always train once
on this data. Yeah.
Okay. So, yeah.
>> Within data mixing, um, do you ever
because like I guess these sources just
happen to align with different topics,
but do you ever take like a diverse data
set and then try to do like data mixing
within that?
>> Yeah.
>> So, the question is uh do you do what do
you apply data mixing to the like
different you know domains or even
within a data set? That's actually I
forgot to mention that. So I'm glad you
brought it up. So in Neotron uh paper
they uh actually in in some of the OMO
stuff as well you basically think about
let's say I give you a just common crawl
right you can actually break this up so
you can group by domain. So they the AI2
folks have this like web organizer so
you can group into topics but you can
also quality filter. Um so then you you
have this like two-dimensional grid
where you have domains and you have
quality and each of these like cells is
something that you would data mix.
So that's one automatic way to determine
the the domains and then on top of that
you add ex extra sources that people
hand you.
Okay. So I'm going to quickly go through
post training uh data here. Um so up
until now this is basically pre-training
or maybe mid-training data. It's
generally fairly task agnostic except
for the reg mix stuff where you're
you're trying to minimize the loss but
still the data itself is still task uh
relatively task agnostic and you're
trying to develop uh basic skills. So
when you look at post- trainining a lot
of the data becomes very kind of task uh
you know dependent um and I'm not going
to do a comprehensive review I just want
to point out some of interesting um
post-raining you know data sets that
have been recently released in
particular for coding since that's uh of
I think great interest these days. Um so
the general recipe
is um you define a set of you know
environments um in the case think about
code which might be GitHub um you know
repos you define a set of uh tasks or or
prompts and then you collect responses
from a strong model or teacher. So
implicitly you know at least in the open
community almost all the post- training
data that's uh most of it is you know
synthetically you know generated
um you can also replace strong model
with uh a human uh but you know that is
slow and costs a lot of money but you
know if you're at the frontier and of um
if you I guess a few years ago you kind
of had to go and pay a lot of people a
lot of money to give you responses. Um,
and nowadays, even at the frontier, you
can do sort of hybrid human AI things.
But anyway, the the point is that
there's some teacher out there that's
giving you responses. Okay. So, um, a
few kind of I'm just going to talk to a
few works here. So, one is this works,
uh, called open thoughts. Um and
this idea here is um this came around it
was motivated by you know when 01 came
out and there was a lot of intention on
reasoning mostly for like math and
science um how do we get really good
post-training data sets for this and um
you know they eventually came out with
1.2 two million examples uh using this
teacher model. Um so the steps are first
of all um there are a bunch of so what
are the environments and the tasks and
questions. Um there are a lot of
different sources um that they they drew
from there human sources like sack
exchange um or num math and then there's
like some synthetic sources as well.
These are just a subset of the the
coding ones, but there's also more for
math and chemistry. This is a big
project that involved a lot of different
uh contributions from many uh people. Um
so you can see that there's um you know
some of these are like coding exercises,
some of these are um you know more
realistic things that show up on um I
guess code golf is not realistic but
there are some more realistic uh um
examples here. Um so code review this is
probably more realistic. Um and they
noticed that they did a fairly
comprehensive uh analysis of you know
given this data set what how do you
generate responses. They show that um
having a few sources was actually good
but rather than trying to do all sources
sampling multiple generations is helpful
like 16. Um one thing that was
interesting is that having better models
um aren't necessarily um you know better
teachers. So for example QWQ 32B which
is you know now a very old and small
model is was a better teacher than
deepseeek R1 which was at the time
probably one of the strongest open
models. Um they also found that basic
answer filtering wasn't helpful. Um
and so the entire pipeline looks
something um you know like this where
you have a bunch of these sources uh you
know going in um and then you you
duplicate you randomly um you know
sample I guess this down sample the
questions and you generate multiple
answers and that gets uh into the final
data set. So the 1.2 2 million isn't um
is examples but divided by 16 gives you
the number of actual questions.
Okay. So there's an another so that was
for um you know math and science and and
some code. Um I think more recently
there's been a lot of interest in
developing in particular a gentic coding
um model. So not just a model that can
just generate some code but actually a
model that can do software development.
Um so this uh Swissmith paper um
um had the idea of you're given a
repository,
you're using an language model to
automatically generate tasks. So they
have an agent that um takes a repository
and actually makes it usable for um uh
like uh installing dependencies and so
on. Um and then you generate tasks which
are generally um you know you modify the
code in some way maybe introduce some
bugs um and those get verified and you
get some task instances. So these are
synthetic tasks um but you get you know
50k of them which is actually um at the
time which was last year uh quite large
um so since then there's been um a bunch
of other uh work which I'll uh
you know mention um so there's this
sweet zero paper from you know Nvidia
um which had this kind of um actually
Okay, I'll also talk about that. So this
is a kind of an interesting idea where
the observation was that unlike math su
task have just a lot of heavy
dependencies. Most GitHub repos like
don't even run and you have to install
all these dependencies and out of date
especially if you roll back to like when
a PR was. It's just kind of a mess. Um
and this is just a nightmare. Um and so
they were thinking about how can we
actually get a data set that just um on
all the the the repos and rather than
having a repo specific docker image um
they noticed that the models are
actually good enough that they can solve
a lot of these tasks without execution
feedback. Um so you know if you look at
some of these uh models if you were
allowing educ execution you get like 80
if you don't allow educa not education
execution you get almost 70. So which is
you know not bad for not being able to
execute code. So um somehow these models
have some internal semantics of of of
code. Um so they were able to generate
300,000 agent trajectories. Um all of
these are real GitHub uh you know PR so
they're realistic unlike the the
Sweenith Smith examples. Um they use the
open hands scaffold and did some there's
a lot of details like how to prevent um
agent hacking. So um normally you uh
hand an agent this um instruction you
explore you test you implement and their
uh 30 version was basically saying you
cannot run Python code you can only do
like set and grap and all these like
basic um um operations.
Okay. So then they distilled from a big
coding model um and filtered um because
sometimes a coding model will ignore
these instructions and still try to
execute anyway. Um and then there they
showed that with this um oh they also
had 13k agent trajectories that do
require execution feedback. So they
train models where they first uh
fine-tune on these sweet zero um
examples and then fine-tune again on
these sweet hero examples and they were
able to you know I guess the frontier is
still pretty uh high up but they were
able to make some you know progress
here. Um I'll quickly go through rebench
was essentially another uh attempt to
grab tons and tons of uh you know uh
PRs. Um, so and all of these kind of
look like get a bunch of GitHub repos,
try to install the repo, like most of
them probably, you know, fail and try
harder and then you use a um a language
model to give you the um the responses.
So in this uh this actually just came
out uh today. Um so you can take the
sweet zero idea and you can now scale up
to 12 million agent trajectories. Um the
nice benefit of three zero is that it's
just you know almost it's very
lightweight. Um here they use the sweet
ben rebench uh tasks. So in this one
remember they were trying to get things
to execute. They only got 32,000 of them
to execute and 120 of them didn't
execute. So you just but zero doesn't
care. you can use all of them. Um this
is a very small model because now this
data set is quite large. Um and so um so
you know I think as you can see the data
sets are you know getting more and more
sophisticated. You go from you know
environment free things like math to now
coding and now the coding data sets are
growing uh quite a bit. Um but the
general idea is that you know you have
these these prompts um which you know
there's kind of trade-offs. You can have
fully synthetic um you can have
semi-ynthetic where you have a real
environment and synthetic tasks or you
can have real um and the responses
generally are coming from just capable
models but they need also need to be
good teachers. Code environments are a
pain and you there's a lot of filtering
and other details which we don't have
time for. Okay, to summarize this
lecture, we talked about filtering. So
define what good looks like and then
train a lightweight classifier. Go over
your web crawl and you can get a a small
subset that matches what you're looking
for. Dduplication is important to avoid
overfitting and saving flops. uh mixing
um try mixture at small scales
extrapolate to large scale um and then
we looked at some you know post-raining
data um I will say that though that a
lot of the data work is can be very
grungy it's very domain specific um and
requires looking at concrete examples to
make these high quality data sets so
this lecture is not really
representative what data work is like
but hopefully I've given you a idea of
the data landscape out there. Okay, that
will be it for today.